[SPEAKER_00]: You mentioned the other day about senses and sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you asked if... can you be disturbed?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there any other... can you be disturbed if there wasn't sense objects?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there any form of emotional disturbance that doesn't involve... doesn't involve the sense objects or senses?
[SPEAKER_00]: But there is no... You can't experience anything else other than senses, sense objects, from that point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't... That's all you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yeah, yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is your mode of being, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why kamabhāva,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a being that arises only when you engage with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when the Buddha talks about three types of being, you should think of them as three types of threshold that your mind might be living on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, three types of domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have the central being, is the most most common one, that's the most, the broadest one, that's what everybody is in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you have the rūpa, rūpa-bhāva and arūpa-bhāva, kama-bhāva, rūpa-bhāva, arūpa-bhāva.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is, these three types of being that the Buddha talks about, three types of bhāva,
[SPEAKER_01]: And, yeah, as you said, sometimes people translate it as becoming, which, again, sort of comes and plays into that view as if only when you are engaging with karma, centrality, that being is becoming.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you stop engaging, that being is not becoming.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can be restrained for the rest of your life and not engage with centrality and still be within the central domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Within the domain of the sensual bhāva.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you're not engaging with chasing the pleasures, your mind is still on the level of... of... on the threshold of senses and sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: It hasn't... hasn't developed beyond that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your mind is resting either on the coarsest, which is sensual domain,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's just to illustrate the point that, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not free from sensuality, your mind is fully within the being of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't mean being of chasing the pleasures wildly.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just means being within sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is your basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is your world.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is your extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, from that point of view, it is impossible for you to experience any form of emotion, any form of feeling, that it will not be rooted
[SPEAKER_01]: Within, upon, that very threshold, that very sense-object basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, practically speaking, that means any disturbance, and I single out disturbance, because that's the whole point of practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not to get the pleasure, but it's to free yourself from suffering, which is the ultimate pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, any form of disturbance, any form of suffering,
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it possible to experience it, unless it's within sense or sense-object, or both?
[SPEAKER_00]: Unless it's because of something on that domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any form of disturbance, even if it's just mental idea of something, it's always going to be, well, boiled down to something you either see, hear, smell, taste, touch, or something you would have to see, hear, smell, taste, touch.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you think about it, when you look at the content of those thoughts, those thoughts, they are now, like, causing a disturbance, is because they imply something disagreeable of seeing, smelling, hearing, tasting, or touching.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even the thoughts are within that central domain, and the content of them is still the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the reason why that is, this is practically relevant, is because, well, the disturbance, any emotional discomfort, always feels like much more.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you were to actually start seeing it correctly as... also, it's just the sight.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I'm resisting here.
[SPEAKER_00]: It always feels much more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it always feels much more, because you always want to... well, you're always trying to get rid of it at face value.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you basically imply there is more to it than there is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why for an arahant, who is fully freed from any craving, any resistance to anything that arises on the level of feeling, in the scene, there is just the scene.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the herd, it's just the herd.
[SPEAKER_01]: There isn't anything else there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there never was.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the pain, there's just the pain?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, in the... well, again, in the pain, there is just the pain, sure, from the point of your feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you want to see, that pain is rooted upon something of the sense kind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sight, sound, smell, taste, touch.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, say, you're experiencing disturbance on account of somebody died.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see, you will never see them again.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, change in the domain of sight.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll never talk to them again.
[SPEAKER_01]: You never get to touch them again.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's basically just deprived deprivation of the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, certain things have changed now and you cannot experience in the same way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that form that you used to see of that person now cannot be seen.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, on account of that sight that has changed, you grieve.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're disturbed.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it is just the sight.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, and always was the sight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you be able to experience love, infatuation, attachment, whatever, towards anyone, if you've never seen them?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you've never heard them?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you've never touched them?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you be able to even think about it?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha said that in many other suttas, just in slightly different contexts, but there was always a point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you have...
[SPEAKER_01]: He asked that man, can you experience lust towards things that were not seen, heard,
[SPEAKER_01]: Not, not basically experience through senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: You say, no, it's impossible to experience lust, those things that I've never seen.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you realize, ah, so things you've never seen, you can't experience lust, which means things you've seen, your lust is fully circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you've seen them, but you could have not seen them, and you will not see them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, not just that kind of puts the objects of your senses in perspective, but puts your own senses back into perspective as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, my own senses are disintegrating slowly, failing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if sense objects are not changing, well, the senses will change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not both can remain unchanged for the duration of your lifetime, let alone longer than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, this will last forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you experience change constantly, on a daily basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you just keep focusing on the pleasant change.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you think about change, ah...
[SPEAKER_01]: But, whenever you suffer, you suffer on account of unpleasant change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, change is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you...
[SPEAKER_00]: If you are longing for a sight...
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you say to yourself, well, that's just a sight?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you want to ask yourself, why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why are you saying that to yourself now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I'm longing for it, I'm suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So longing is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So are you saying, that's just a sight, so you don't experience displeasure?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that I can force that idea into my mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, but that's... you can do literally anything from any sutta, if you do it like that, you'll be doing it wrongly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Although you're doing what the sutta says,
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not doing it rightly, so you will not get the benefit from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you shouldn't be trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is an experience, the threshold, is you are emotionally engaged with the domain of sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're longing for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Longing for it, wanting it, not wanting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, you and the sight, there is a relationship there, on account of which you feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to accept that as a starting point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like, oh, I must get rid of this, I must deal with this.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That has arisen on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only thing you must do is understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I say understand it, I don't mean understand some hypothesis that arises on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understand the nature of that relationship.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the nature of longing for a sight?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it implies the necessity of your sense bases, as in your eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it implies the presence of your eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: That pressure to go and see something you want, or the pressure to avoid seeing something you don't want.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't have the eyes, none of that's applicable anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, part of the understanding of that relationship is understanding the gratuity of eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eyes see.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're subjected to what they see.
[SPEAKER_00]: But do you have control over your eyes?
[SPEAKER_01]: Remind yourself of that context of...
[SPEAKER_01]: These eyes are these lumpy flesh, balls of flesh in the world, like all these other random things, on account of which I get sights.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I have no...
[SPEAKER_01]: Fundamentally, I have no control over my eyes in a sense of...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not their owner.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't prevent them from suddenly not working anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or seeing something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or seeing something I don't want to see, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, if you were truly a master, you would only see things you want to see.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would be the master of that which arises on account of the eyes, which is sights.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yet, here you are, grieving on account of sights.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, when we talk about understanding, it's not about discerning some theoretical relationship and meaning, or secret.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's literally
[SPEAKER_01]: Drilling in, repetitively, the obviousness of the nature of these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, I say the obviousness, because it's obvious, and because it's obvious, people don't think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not enough to see that it's obvious that eyes are not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to now keep repeat that same obvious seeing, well, for as long as you have lust in regard to sights left.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, if you understood that correctly, it's impossible to experience lust towards sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or disturbance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any form of disturbance, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's because you don't see the nature of your senses... Because you haven't understood it, that's why you're still disturbed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the obviousness of it should not fool you into thinking, okay, I got this, what next?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I got it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does that mean I'm free from sensuality?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can a sight disturb me in the future?
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to keep reflecting.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what the Buddha would always say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, you practice, you have insights, things start making sense, but that's only part of the picture.
[SPEAKER_01]: The other part is, you keep asking yourself, okay, so can unarisen sensuality arise now in me?
[SPEAKER_01]: Does the reason sensuality last less, less, like, like, for a short amount of time?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is my mind quicker to free?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all of these things you reflect to see, oh, am I actually free or is just kind of a temporary I made sense out of anything and I got a relief?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of that experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to, you want that understanding to also prevent you from being disturbed in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just freeing you from whatever was disturbing you while you were thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I want, like, your eyes
[SPEAKER_00]: What you see, do not disturb me.
[SPEAKER_01]: You mean, my eyes do not disturb you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, my eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is that... but understanding my eyes, in that same way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to start seeing your eyes, pretty much like other people's eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like a stranger's.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just, your eyes is the closest to your point of view, than other people's eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But either way, eyes are there, sights are there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yeah, your eyes are not more yours than my eyes are.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're just closer.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're closer in their arrangement, whichever way you experience the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because of that proximity, oh, this is mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there's nothing else between me and this.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a lot in between me and your eyes, but between me and my eyes, there's nothing in between.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just I see.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the sense bases are always described in that kind of negative terms, like as absent, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're defined by things you see.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't see your eyes, but the eyes are there because of which you see.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't hear your ears, because there's nothing, nothing in between you, nothing that you can perceive between you and your sense bases.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why the ownership of the entire world is rooted upon the ownership of the senses and the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, removing that ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Removing the ownership through seeing that these things operate on their own.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't even know about you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't exist for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eyes don't know about Vendra Bhattacharya.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eyes just keep seeing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all they see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep avoiding the disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep looking the agreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when you don't
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't own them anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see their nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: They still will go for what is agreeable to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what is disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is disagreeable, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... Because agreeable and disagreeable, fundamentally, does not require lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is no lust without agreeable or disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, agreeable and disagreeable is what senses do.
[SPEAKER_01]: You
[SPEAKER_01]: Taking the ownership, assuming the ownership of the senses, you are then pulled by agreeable and repelled by disagreeable, as in there is lust there, there is aversion there, there is delusion, distraction there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you remove the ownership, there is no more lust towards agreeable, there is no more aversion towards disagreeable, and there is no more distraction towards neutral.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what's stopping the eye from going
[SPEAKER_01]: Absence of lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no passion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, see, this is an agreeable sight and it stops there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your mind infected with lust that then wants more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wants to taste it, wants to touch it, wants to have it, wants to whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's disagreeable, wants to destroy it, wants to kill it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those are not senses anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now it's you completely blowing up on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's lust and aversion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is still the basis of disagree... oh, there's still a disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is still agreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you have no lust, nor aversion, that cannot become more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this is disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is annoying, harassing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you turn away.
[SPEAKER_01]: You turn away.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the end of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even then, you don't turn away because you're averse towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the only reason you're too averse towards it, is because you sort of overreached in regard to your own senses as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what else is there to blame?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's the things that are disturbing these senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if your senses are not yours, you would not blame sense objects for anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's say a disagreeable sight arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am not free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's your starting point.
[SPEAKER_01]: The discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, first thing you do is, okay, I must not act out of trying to get rid of the discomfort, because that's going to be another just acting out of aversion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it's, but I practice dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the only way you can practice dhamma is to not be rooted in craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you're trying to get rid of the aversion that has arisen on account of disagreeable sight, you are rooted in craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, there will be no dhamma you practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter how much you think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, first, what is the present situation for you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's the disagreeable feeling on account of unpleasant sight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or unpleasant feeling on account of disagreeable sight, better.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like I said before, you get pain in the knee.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I won't move now, because if I move, I'm averse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm craving to get rid of the pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'll just stick with this pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you're craving to not get rid of the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, you're affected by pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what do I do then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, first, you allow that thing to endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, don't just blindly move.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, if it's a problem, but then you reflect.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Body is subjected to discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is this body mine?
[SPEAKER_01]: To what extent is mine?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I'm not sure if it's mine or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if it's yours, would you be experiencing any discomfort?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's clearly the sort of... the pathway where body, as sense organs, experiences corresponding senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are not privy to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all you have is, I meet the sights somewhere in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if you are aware of it, you get the corresponding pressure, so to speak, contact.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only reason you know that eye has met the sight, not because you witnessed eye meeting the sights, which is usually a mistake and misconception of how the contact arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only reason you know that is because you're already pressured.
[SPEAKER_01]: On account of the pressure of the visual, you know that eyes have seen.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that eyes and seeing, you cannot get in between that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you shut your eyelids, you're seeing the inner side of your eyelids.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eyes are always seeing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's inconceivable for you to prevent eyes from seeing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can then that be thoroughly, in any shape or form, yours?
[SPEAKER_01]: When you don't even know how these things come together.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're only subjected, as I said, to the pressure resulting of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, by the way, that pressure is because you already gratuitously, foolishly own it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Own that which is invisible to you, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: Plenty of things to reflect upon, correctly, without trying to get rid of that uncomfortable pressure of the disagreeable sides.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's what feeling is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pressure towards pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pressure towards pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Away from pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pressure towards oblivion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the body will still move away.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: It'll shift.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It'll shift.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and you wouldn't have to overthink it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, look!
[SPEAKER_01]: The body moved, because the knee was hurting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I didn't even think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't need you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It never did.
[SPEAKER_00]: I said that before.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... you are like that...
[SPEAKER_00]: I was an unwanted guest, but you're a guest in this party that's not even... nobody else knows you're even there.
[SPEAKER_00]: No one cares that you're there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the first one is right.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that no one cares, because I don't care.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're invisible.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're invisible to everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same to the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Take any of your aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't exist for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's because of that that Arahantship's possible in the first place.